本片由【天主的译站】字幕组校对，
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695指导交流!
此字幕仅限于交流学习，不可用做商业用途！
校对人员：A愈显主荣Ω
他被刺透，是因了我们的悖逆
他被打伤，是因了我们的罪恶
因他受了创伤，我们便得了痊愈
依撒意亚先知书 53章      公元前700年
伯多禄
Peter.
你们竟不能同我醒寤一个时辰吗？
You could not watch even one hour with me?
辣彼，你怎么了？
Master, what has happened to you?
主，要不要叫醒其他人？
Should l call the others, Lord?
算了，若望，我不想让他们见到我这个样子
No, John. l don't want them to see me like this.
你有危险吗？老师，我们要不要逃走？
Are you in danger? Should we flee, Master?
留在这里，醒寤...
Stay here. Watch...
...祈祷
...pray.
他怎么了？
What is wrong with him?
他好像很害怕
He seems afraid.
刚才吃饭时他提到有危险...
He had spoken about danger while we ate...
说什么背叛出卖...
He mentioned betrayal and...
三十块银钱
Thirty.
三十，茹达斯
Thirty, Judas.
这是你我讲好的价钱是吗？
That was the agreement between me...and you?
是的
Yes.
在哪？
Where?
他在哪？
Where is he?
父啊，求你俯听我的哀号
Hear me, Father.
求你振奋起来予我救助
Rise up, defend me.
救我脱离他们为我暗设的罗网
Save me from the traps they set for me.
你真的相信...
Do you really believe...
一个人能够背负...
...that one man can bear...
...世上所有的罪吗？
...the full burden of sin?
主啊，求你庇护我
Shelter me, O Lord.
我信赖你
l trust in You.
我投靠你
ln You l take refuge.
这个重担谁也挑不起...
No one man can carry this burden...
我告诉你
...l tell you.
这担子太沉重了
lt is far too heavy.
救赎世人的灵魂代价太高了
Saving their souls is too costly.
没有一个人办得到
No one. Ever.
没有
No.
从来没有
Never.
父啊，一切为你都可能
Father, you can do all things.
你如果愿意，请给我免去这杯吧...
lf it is possible, let this chalice pass from me...
惟照你的意愿成就吧...
But let Your will be done...
...不要随我的意愿
...not mine.
你的父亲是谁？
Who is your father?
你又是谁？
Who are you?
你们找谁？
Who are you looking for?
纳匝肋人耶稣
We're looking for Jesus of Nazareth.
我就是
l am he.
辣彼，你好
Hail, Rabbi!
茹达斯...
Judas...
你用口亲来负卖人子吗？
...you betray the Son of Man with a kiss?
伯多禄
Peter!
把刀放下
Put it down!
凡持剑的，必死在剑下
Those who live by the sword shall die by the sword.
把剑放回原处
Put it down.
玛耳曷，起来
Malchus! Get up!
逮到他了 ，我们走
We've got him. Let's go!
怎么了，玛利亚？怎么了？
What, Mary? What is it?
你听...
Listen...
今夜为何跟往常不一样？
''Why is this night different from every other night?''
因为以前我们是奴隶
''Because once we were slaves...
以后就不在是了！
''...and we are slaves no longer...''
他们把他抓走了！
They've seized him !
大家听着，去大司祭的庭院集合
Everyone you can, hear? To the courtyard of the High Priest.
快！走！
Quick! Go!
停! 别太快
Halt! Not so fast.
你凑什么热闹，人渣
This is not your party, you toothless vermin.
伯多禄...
Peter...
喂，怎么回事？
Hey! What's going on here?
在那边! 阻止他们!
ln there! Stop them !
他们把他抓起来了!
They've arrested him !
秘密的! 在夜里!
ln secret! ln the night!
想要掩饰他们的罪行！
To hide their crime from you!
阻止他们！
Stop them !
这女子在乱叫什么?
What are you yelling about, woman?
他们抓了谁?
Who have they arrested?
耶稣
Jesus.
纳匝肋人耶稣！
Jesus of Nazareth!
闭嘴！
Shut up!
她是疯子
She's crazy.
只是捉个罪犯进来拷问罢了
A criminal. Brought in for questioning, that's all.
他犯了圣殿的律法
Broke the temple laws.
原来如此
l see.
快去禀告他会出大的乱子
Better go tell him there's more trouble brewing.
禀告谁呀？
Tell who?
百夫长啊，蠢材
Abenader, you idiot.
快去
Get going!
去呀
Go!
耶稣...
Jesus...
你饿了吗？
Are you hungry?
是的，我饿了
Yes, l am.
这张桌子好高啊
This is certainly a tall table!
替谁做的？
Who is it for?
一个有钱人
A rich man.
他喜欢站着吃吗？
Does he like to eat standing up?
不，他喜欢这样吃
No. He prefers to eat like...so.
高桌配高椅
Tall table, tall chairs!
但椅子还没动工
Well, l haven't made them yet.
这种桌子不会流行！
This will never catch on!
不，你休想
Oh, no you don't!
把脏围裙脱了再进屋里
Take off that dirty apron before you come in.
还要洗手
And wash your hands.
主啊，已经开始了
lt has begun, Lord.
那就来吧
So be it.
长官，出事了 ，就在...
Sir, there's trouble at...
百夫长，深更半夜出什么事？
What, in the middle of the night, Abenader?
对不起
l'm sorry.
怎么回事？
What's the problem?
城里有骚动
Trouble within the walls.
盖法捉了一位先知
Caiphas had some prophet arrested.
谁？
Who?
是个加里肋亚人
Some Galilean.
法利塞人显然痛恨这个人
The Pharisees apparently hate the man.
加里肋亚人？你说的是谁？
A Galilean? Who are you talking about?
你押解来的这个叫花子是谁？
Who is this beggar you bring to us...
带着镣铐像个服刑的罪犯
...chained up like a condemned man?
他叫耶稣，是纳匝肋的祸害
He's Jesus, the Nazarene troublemaker.
你就是纳匝肋人耶稣？
You're Jesus of Nazareth?
有人说你是王
They say you're a king.
你的国在哪里？
Where is this kingdom of yours?
是哪个君王的子孙？
What line of kings do you descend from?
回话
Speak up!
你不是穷木匠的儿子吗？
You're just the son of some obscure carpenter, no?
有人说你是厄里亚
Some say you're Elijah.
但他早已驾战车上天了
But he was carried off to heaven in a chariot!
怎么不回话呢？
Why don't you say something?
你因为亵渎天主所以被押到这里
You've been brought here as a blasphemer!
你有什么话说？
What do you say to that?
为自己辩护啊
Defend yourself.
我向来公开地对世人讲话
l have spoken openly to everyone.
我常常在...
l've taught...
...犹太人聚集的地方施教
...in the temple where we all gather.
你问那些听过我的人，我给他们讲了什么
Ask those who have heard what l have to say.
你就这样答复大司祭吗？
ls that how you address the high priest?
傲慢无礼?
With arrogance?
我若说的不对
lf l have spoken evil...
...你指证哪里不对.
...tell me what evil l have said.
若对，你为什么打我？
But if not, why do you hit me?
好，让我们听听你说过的亵渎的话
Yes, we'll listen to those who heard your blasphemies.
好了！
Good!
我们就听听看.
Let's hear them.
他用邪术给人治病！
He cures the sick by magic!
靠魔鬼的帮助！
With the help of devils!
我亲眼见到.
l've seen it.
他靠魔鬼的力量驱魔.
He casts out devils, with the help of devils.
他自称是犹太人的国王！
He calls himself the king of the Jews!
不，他说自己是天主子！
No, he calls himself the son of God!
他扬言要拆毁圣殿...
He said he would destroy the temple...
...并在三天内把它重建起来！
...and rebuild it in three days!
还有更荒唐的!
Worse!
他宣称他是生命之粮！
He claims he's the bread of life!
要是我们不吃他的肉喝他的血...
And if we don't eat his flesh or drink his blood...
就得不到永生.
...we won't inherit eternal life.
肃静!
Silence!
你们都被他蛊惑了
You're all under this man's spell.
如果没有他有罪的证据...
Either offer proof of his wrongdoing...
就给我闭嘴!
...or be quiet!
这整个审讯太荒唐了
This entire proceeding is an outrage.
这些人说的都是无稽之谈 自相矛盾!
All l've heard from these witnesses is mindless contradiction!
是谁召集的这场公审会？
Who called this meeting anyway?
这么晚还劳师动众？
And at this hour of the night?
其他的公议会的人员呢？
Where are the other members of the council?
把他赶出去！
Get him out of here!
出去！
Get out!
胡闹，简直是一场粗暴的闹剧
A travesty! That's what this is, a beastly travesty!
你什么也不回答吗？
Haven't you anything to say?
关于这些人作证反对你的事？
No answer to these accusations?
那么我现在问你
l ask you now...
纳匝肋人耶稣
...Jesus of Nazareth...
告诉我们，你是不是默西亚？
Tell us, are you the Messiah?
永生天主之子？
The son of the living God?
我是
l AM...
...你们将要看见人子坐在大能者的右边
...and you will see the Son of Man seated at the right hand of power...
...乘着天上的云彩降来.
...and coming on the clouds of heaven.
亵渎！
Blasphemy!
你们都听见了
You heard him.
何必还需要再找见证呢!
There's no need for witnesses!
判决，你们以为该怎么样？
Your verdict. What is your verdict?
他该死！
Death!
你不是同那加里肋亚人一伙吗？
Haven't l seen you in the company of the Galilean?
没错，你也是他门徒中的一个！
Yes! You're one of his disciples!
我认得你！
l recognize you!
闭嘴，我没见过他，我不认识他
Quiet! l've never met the man. l don't know him.
你是伯多禄，是耶稣门徒中的一个.
You are Peter! One of the disciples of Jesus.
我不认得那个人！你弄错了！
l don't know the man! You are wrong!
站住，别跑
Stop! Stop!
我以前见过你！
l've seen you before!
拦住他！他跟他们一伙！
Stop him ! He's one of them !
该死，你弄错了！
You're wrong, damn you!
我发誓不认识那个人.
l swear l don't know the man.
我从来没见过他.
l've never seen him before.
主啊，无论你往哪里去...
Wherever you go, Lord...
...我都要跟随你.
...l will follow.
同你一起下狱，同去受死.
To prison, even to death.
我实在告诉你...
Amen, l say to you...
...今夜鸡叫以前...
...before the cock crows...
...你要三次不认我.
...three times you will deny me.
伯多禄？
Peter?
不要...我不配!
No, no...l am unworthy!
我否认了他，母亲！
l have denied him, Mother!
我有三次不敢认他.
Denied him three times.
我们走！去处理这件事.
Let's go! You take care of it.
让他过来.他是个没用的东西.
Let him pass. He's harmless.
放了他!
Release him !
银钱还给你.
Take back the silver.
拿去!
Here!
我出卖了无辜的血，我有罪了.
l've sinned, betrayed innocent blood.
把钱拿回去.这与我有什么关系！
Take back your silver. l don't want it!
如果你觉得你出卖了无辜的血，是你自己的事.
lf you think you've betrayed innocent blood, that's your affair.
拿着你的钱走吧.
Take your money and go.
滚！
Now go!
你怎么了？没事吧？
What's wrong? Are you all right?
看他的嘴，让我们看看？
Look at his mouth. Hey, can we look at it?
要不要我们帮忙？
You need help? Can we help?
他流血了！快看！血！
He's bleeding! Look! Blood!
别烦我...
Leave me alone...
...你们这些小恶魔!
...you little satans!
啊！诅咒，你被诅咒了？
Aha ! Cursing! Are you cursed?
他被诅咒了
He's cursed!
对 诅咒! 就在他身上 看呀!
Yes, a curse! lt's inside him, look!
小心 他体内像滚油煎熬!
Watch out, it's like burning oil from his bones!
走开! 别来碰我!
Get away from me! Leave me alone!
不要定这个加里肋亚人的罪.
Don't condemn this Galilean.
他是圣洁者.
He's holy.
那样做只会替你自己惹来麻烦.
You will only bring trouble on yourself.
你知道我认为的麻烦是什么吗 克劳蒂亚？
Do you want to know my idea of trouble, Claudia?
在这鬼地方和管理外面那些暴民.
This stinking outpost, that filthy rabble out there.
你们都是先拷打然后才审判？
Do you always punish your prisoners before they're judged?
总督大人...
Governor...
你们对这人提出什么控告？
What accusations do you bring against this man?
这个...
Well...
如果这人不是作恶的，我们便不会把他交给你.
lf he weren't a malefactor, we wouldn't have brought him before you.
我不是问这个.
That's not what l asked.
你们为何不按照你们的法律审判他？
Why don't you judge him according to your own laws?
大人，你知道我们是不许...
Consul, you know it's unlawful for us...
...处死任何人的.
...to condemn any man to death.
判死刑？
To death?
这个人究竟做了什么，要判他死刑？
What has this man done to merit such a penalty?
他不守安息日.
He has violated our Sabbath, Consul.
继续...
Go on...
他妖言惑众
He has seduced the people...
...教坏人民，宣传邪说.
...taught foul, disgusting doctrines.
五天前，难道不是你们把他当先知迎进耶路撒冷？
lsn't he the prophet you welcomed into Jerusalem only five days ago?
现在却要杀他，谁能解释一下这疯狂的举动?
And now you want him dead? Can any of you explain this madness to me?
总督大人 请听我说...
Your Excellency, please...
大司祭还没向你禀报他的重罪
So far the high priest hasn't told you this man's greatest crime.
他是一群危险份子的领导
He has become the leader of a large and dangerous sect...
...他们称呼他大卫的后裔
...who hail him as the Son of David!
他自称是默西亚...
He claims that he is the Messiah...
...天主预许的犹太人的国王.
...the king promised to the Jews.
他还阻止追随者给凯撒纳税.
He has forbidden his followers to pay tribute to the emperor, Consul!
带他上来！
Bring him here!
下去！
Go!
喝吧.
Drink.
你是犹太人的君王吗？
Are you the king of the Jews?
这话是你由自己说的？
Does this question come from you?
或是别人论我而对你说的？
Or do you ask me this because others have told you that is what l am?
我不是要问你这个？
Why would l ask you that?
莫非我是犹太人？
Am l a Jew?
你的民族和司祭长把你交付给我.
Your high priests, your own people delivered you up to me.
他们要我处决你.
They want me to have you executed.
为什么，你作了什么？
Why? What have you done?
你是不是王？
Are you a king?
我的国不属于这世界.
My kingdom is not of this world.
假使我的国属于这世界...
lf it were...
...我的臣民早已反抗了，使我不至于被交给犹太人？
...do you think my followers would have let them hand me over?
那么，你就是君王了？
Then you are a king?
我为此而生.
That is why l was born.
为给真理作证.
To give testimony to the truth.
凡属于真理的，必听从我的声音.
All men who hear the truth hear my voice.
真理！
Truth!
什么是真理？
What is truth?
我已经问过了，我在这人身上查不出什么罪状来.
l have questioned this prisoner, and l find no cause in him.
他不是加里肋亚人吗？
This man is a Galilean, is he not?
是的.
He is.
那么他归黑落德王管.
Then he is King Herod's subject.
让黑落德审判他.
Let Herod judge him.
总督...
Governor...
把他交给黑落德.
Hand him over.
纳匝肋人耶稣！
Jesus of Nazareth!
在哪里？
Where?
他在哪里？
Where is he?
这就是...
This...
...纳匝肋人耶稣？
...is Jesus of Nazareth?
你当真使瞎眼的看得见？
ls it true that you restore sight to the blind?
...叫死人复活？
Raise men from the dead?
你的能力从哪来的？
Where do you get your power?
预言中要降世的人就是你？
Are you the one whose birth was foretold?
回答我！
Answer me!
你是不是君王？
Are you a king?
那我算什么？
How about me?
行个神迹给我看好吗？
Will you work a little miracle for me?
把这个傻子带走.
Take this stupid fool out of my sight.
他没有罪，他只是疯了.
He's not guilty of a crime, he's just crazy.
给他傻子的待遇...
Give him a fool's homage...
克劳蒂亚，真理是什么？
What is truth, Claudia?
听到真理时,你能明白吗？
Do you hear it, recognize it when it is spoken?
是的，我懂.
Yes, l do.
你听不懂吗？
Don't you?
如何明白？
How?
你能教我吗？
Can you tell me?
你若听不懂真理，别人要教你也难.
lf you will not hear the truth, no one can tell you.
真理...
Truth...
你想知道我的真理吗 克劳蒂亚?
Do you want to know what my truth is, Claudia?
我在这鬼地方镇压叛乱已经11年了
l've been putting down rebellions in this rotten outpost for eleven years.
要是我不判这人有罪...
lf l don't condemn this man...
...盖法肯定会带头兴风作浪.
...l know Caiphas will start a rebellion.
我若判他有罪，他的信众又会闹事.
lf l do condemn him, then his followers may.
不论怎么做,都会有人流血.
Either way, there will be bloodshed.
凯撒警告过我，克劳蒂亚，警告过两次.
Caesar has warned me, Claudia. Warned me twice.
他说下次就该轮到我流血了.
He swore that the next time the blood would be mine.
这就是我的真理!
That is my truth!
黑落德不肯判这人有罪.他们把他带了回来.
Herod refuses to condemn the man. They're bringing him back here.
我们需要兵力增援.
We're going to need reinforcements.
我不想再引起任何暴动.
l don't want to cause an uprising.
暴动已经开始了.
There is already an uprising.
黑落德王找不出这人的罪状.
King Herod found no cause in this man.
我也一样.
Neither do l.
来人，看住他们!
Men! Attend to the crowd!
肃静！
Quiet!
难道你们不尊敬我们的罗马总督?
Have you no respect for our Roman procurator?
你们知道，每年我该给你们释放一个犯人.
As you know, every year l release a criminal back to you.
我们现在有一个罪大恶极的杀人犯...
We are now holding a notorious murderer...
...巴辣巴.
...Barabbas.
你们愿意我给你们释放哪一个？
Which of the two men would you have me release to you?
杀人犯巴辣巴?
The murderer Barabbas?
还是人称默西亚的耶稣？
Or Jesus, called the Messiah?
他不是默西亚！是冒牌货！亵渎者！
He is not the Messiah! He is an imposter! A blasphemer!
释放巴辣巴！
Free Barabbas!
我再问一次，这两个人你们要我释放哪一个？
Again l ask you: which of these two men should l release to you?
释放巴辣巴！
Free Barabbas!
释放他.
Free him.
那你们要我怎么处置纳匝肋人耶稣？
What would you have me do with Jesus the Nazarene?
钉他在十字架上!
Have him crucified!
不行!
No!
我会鞭打他...
l will chastise him...
...然后再放了他.
...but then l will set him free.
百夫长，给我重重地打.
See to it that the punishment is severe, Abenader.
但别让他们打死他.
But don't let them kill the man.
父啊，我的心已准备妥当...
My heart is ready, Father...
...我的心已准备妥当.
...my heart is ready.
我儿...
My son...
...你何时、何地、才能...
...when, where, how...
...脱离这苦难？
...will you choose to be delivered of this?
世界若恨你们...
lf the world hates you...
...你们该知道，在你们以前，它已恨了我.
...remember that it has hated me first.
要记住，没有仆人大过主人的.
Remember also that no servant is greater than his master.
如果他们迫害了我，也要迫害你们.
lf they persecuted me, they will persecute you.
不要害怕.
You must not be afraid.
护慰者...
The Helper will come...
...也就是真理之神会来...
...who reveals the truth about God...
...由父而发出的.
...and who comes from the Father.
住手
Stop!
够了！让你们打他...
Enough! Your orders were to punish this man...
...但不是将他打死！
...not to scourge him to death!
把他带走.
Take him away.
快点！
Get going!
把他带走！
Get him out of here!
陛下...
Your majesty...
小心了.
Take care of it.
一顶美丽的玫瑰花冠.
A beautiful rose bush.
看，犹太人的君王！
Look at him...king of the worms!
犹太人的君王，万岁！
Hail, wormy king!
这颜色最适合君王！
A color fit for a king!
我们来朝拜你了.
We're here to pay our respects.
众兄弟们的领袖!
A leader for our brotherhood!
看，这个人.
Behold the man.
钉他在十字架上！
Crucify him !
这还不够吗？看看他！
lsn't this enough? Look at him !
钉他在十字架上！
Crucify him !
要我把你们的君王钉在十字架上吗？
Shall l crucify your king?
除了凯撒，我们没有君王！
We have no king but Caesar!
回答我.
Speak to me.
我有权柄钉你在十字架上，也有权柄释放你.
l have the power to crucify you, or else to set you free.
若不是由上赐给你...
You have no power over me...
...你对我什么权柄也没有.
...except what is given you from above.
为此，把我交付给你的人...
Therefore, it is he who delivered me to you...
...负罪更大.
...who has the greater sin.
总督大人，你如果释放他...
lf you free him, Governor...
...你就不是凯撒的朋友.
...you are no friend of Caesar's.
你一定要钉死他！
You must crucify him !
要钉死他的是你们，不是我.
lt is you who want to crucify him, not l. Look you to it.
对这义人的血，我是无罪的.
l am innocent of this man's blood.
百夫长...
Abenader...
照他们的意思做.
Do as they wish.
父啊，我是你的仆役，你仆役是你婢女的儿子.
l am your servant, Father. Your servant, and the son of Your handmaid.
为何不拥抱你的十字架，傻子？
Why do you embrace your cross, fool?
好了，陛下，咱们走吧！
All right, your highness, let's move!
想办法让我接近他.
Help me get near him.
走这边.
This way.
走这边，母亲.
This way, Mother.
母亲...
Mother...
我在这里...
l'm here...
母亲，看，我已更新了一切.
See, mother, l make all things new.
那人是谁？
Who is that?
谁？
Who?
那个加利肋亚人的母亲.
She's the Galilean's mother.
我们走.
Let's go.
快!
Come on!
不要难过，我的女儿.
Don't fret, my daughter.
不要难过.
Don't fret.
你们都瞎了吗？
Are you blind?
难道没看到他走不动了？
Can't you see, he can't go on?
帮下他!
Help him !
你！
You!
对，就是你！过来！
Yes, you! Get over here!
找我干什么？
What do you want from me?
这个犯人已经抬不动十字架了.
This criminal can't carry his cross by himself anymore.
你帮忙扛！快点！
You will help him ! Now get going!
我不干，这与我无关，找别人.
l can't do that. lt's none of my business. Get someone else!
帮帮他！他是圣者.
Help him ! He is a holy man.
照我的话去做 现在就去！快!
Do as l tell you. Now move! Let's go!
好吧，可是记住...
All right, but remember...
...我不是罪犯，被逼着去帮一个犯人抬十字架!
...l'm an innocent man, forced to carry the cross of a condemned man.
你在这里等我.
Stay here. Wait for me.
主啊，让我服侍你.
Permit me, my Lord.
你是什么东西？
Who do you think you are?
走开.
Get away from here.
一群乱民!
lmpossible people!
来人呀，阻止他们！
Someone stop this!
住手，住手！
Stop! Stop!
别再虐待他了！
Leave him alone!
再不住手，我就不帮他背十字架了.
lf you don't stop, l won't carry that cross one more step.
要怎么处置随你们！
l don't care what you do to me!
好了，好了，我们上路.
All right, all right, let's get moving.
我们可不想耗一整天.走！
We don't have all day. Let's go!
走...
Let's go...
...犹太人！
...Jew!
快到了.
Almost there.
我们就快到了
We're nearly there.
快到了.
Almost done.
你们一向听说过...
You have heard it said...
...你应爱你的近人，恨你的仇人。
...you shall love your neighbor and hate your enemy.
我却对你们说...
But l say to you...
...你们当爱你们的仇人，当为迫害你们的人祈祷...
...love your enemies and pray for those who persecute you...
你们若只爱那爱你们的人...
For if you love only those who love you...
...你们还有什么赏报呢？
...what reward is there in that?
我是善牧.
l am the good shepherd.
善牧为羊舍掉自己的性命.
l lay down my life for my sheep.
谁也不能夺去我的性命...
No one takes my life from me...
...而是我甘心情愿舍掉它.
...but l lay it down of my own accord.
我有权舍掉它...
l have power to lay it down...
...我也有权再取回它来.
...and power to take it up again.
这是我由我父所接受的命令.
This command is from my Father.
走开，你可以走了.走！快走！
Get away now, you're free to go. Go on! Go on!
你现在可以起来了！
You can get up now!
起来，陛下.
Get up, your majesty.
你起不来吗？
Can't you get up?
我们可没时间跟你耗.
We haven't got all day.
快点，我们准备好了.
Come on, move! We're ready.
起来，陛下.
Get up, your highness.
你们是我的朋友.
You are my friends.
人若为自己的朋友舍掉性命，再没有比这更大的爱情了.
There is no greater love than for a man to lay down his life for his friends.
我同你们在一起的时候不多了.
l cannot be with you much longer, my friends.
我所去的地方，你们不能去.
You cannot go where l am going.
我给你们一条新命令...
My commandment to you after l am gone is this...
你们该彼此相爱.
Love one another.
如同我爱了你们...
As l have loved you...
...你们也该照样彼此相爱.
...so love one another.
你们要信赖我.
You believe in me.
你们知道我就是道路...
You know that l am the Way...
...真理，生命.
...the Truth, and the Life.
除非经过我，谁也不能到父那里去.
And no one comes to the Father but by me.
拉长点儿...
Further out...
笨蛋，我做给你看.
ldiots! Let me show you how to do it.
就像这样！
Like this!
这里！不对 要钉进洞里 像这样把手掌打开.
There! No, get in there. Hold the hand open like this.
父啊，宽赦他们吧...
Father, forgive them...
父啊...
Father...
...父啊我父...我天主...
...Father my Father...my God...
他们不知道...他们不知道...（他们做的是什么）
They don't know...they don't know...
没用的家伙！
Stupid mongrels!
翻过来让他脸朝下，笨蛋！
Turn the wood over on its face, idiots!
你们拿着吃
Take this and eat.
这是我的身体，为你们而舍弃的.
This is my body which is given up for you.
你们大家拿去喝.
Take this and drink.
这是我的血，新而永久盟约之血...
This is my blood of the new covenant...
...将为你们和众人倾流，以赦免罪过.
...which is given for you and for many, for the forgiveness of sins.
你们要这样做来纪念我.
Do this in memory of me.
如果你是天主子，为何不救你自己？
lf you are the son of God, why don't you save yourself?
证明给我们看...
Prove to us...
...你是你所说的那人.
...you are who you say you are.
你说你能拆毁圣殿...
You said you could destroy the temple...
...三天内重建起来...
...and rebuild it in three days...
...现在却不能从十字架下来.
...and yet you cannot come down from that cross.
他若是默西亚...
lf he is the Messiah...
...现在可以从十字架下来...
...l say let him come down from the cross...
...叫我们看了好相信.
...so that we may see and believe.
父啊，宽赦他们吧...
Father, forgive them...
...他们不知道他们做的是什么.
...they know not what they do.
你们听...
Listen...
...他为你们祈祷.
...he prays for you.
我们是罪有应得，狄思玛斯...
We deserve this, Gesmas...
...但他不该受刑.
...but he does not.
我有罪...
l have sinned...
...我受这种刑罚是罪有应得.
...and my punishment is just.
你有理由责难我.
You would be justified in condemning me.
主啊，当你来为王时...
l ask only that you remember me, Lord...
...请你纪念我.
...when you enter your kingdom.
我实在告诉你...
Amen, l tell you...
...今天你就要与我...
...on this day you shall be with me...
...一同在乐园里.
...in paradise.
我渴.
l thirst.
我的肉中肉...
Flesh of my flesh...
...心头的肉...
...heart of my heart...
我儿啊，让我与你同死.
My son, let me die with you.
女人...
Woman...
...看，你的儿子.
...behold your son.
儿子，看...
Son, behold...
...你的母亲.
...your mother.
人群都散了.
There is no one left.
都走光了 ，耶稣！
No one, Jesus!
我的天主...
My God...
你为什么舍弃了我？
...why have you forsaken me?
完成了.
lt is accomplished.
父啊，我把我的灵魂...
Father, into your hands...
交托在你手中.
...l commend...my spirit.
快点！卡休斯！
Cassius! Hurry!
他已经死了!
He's dead!
确定一下！
Make sure!